In this video, we will be talking about
electric
field lines. So, what are electric field
lines?
Electric field lines is the electric
charge
in a certain direction. Electric field
lines
for positively charged objects point
outside,
while electric field charges for
negatively
go towards negatively charged objects.
And in this case, we're going to be
dealing
with point charges, which are charges with
no
mass. They're just charges in space.
When you put two charges or two point
charges
close together, the electric field will
change
depending on what type of charges they
are.
For example, if you put a positive and a
negatively
charged object together, the electric
field
lines will go away from the positively
charged
object towards the negatively charged
object.
If you put two positives together, they'll
repel
each other and they will go sort of like
this.
Electric field is quantifiable and it's
given
by the equation E equals k q over r
squared, which is kind of like what we've
learned
before about Coulomb's law. But instead,
this
time there is only one charge. This is
because
this electric field measures the electric
field
of one single point charge instead of two
different
objects. So, electric
fields are a really good way of depicting
how
charges interact with each other, and they
can
also be quantifiable in the diagram.
Let's say we have a positive charge.
Let's call this charge A. And in our
diagram,
let's say A only has five arrows going
away
from it. However, charge B, or six arrows,
sure.
However, charge B only has three arrows
going
away from it. And the number of arrows, or
the
density of the electric fields in the
diagram,
depict how strong the charge is.
If the charge of A, qA, is equal to five,
or let's say if the charge of A is equal
to
10 Coulombs, then the charge of B would be
equal
to half that because the number of lines
is
half of A. So the charge of B is equal to
five
Coulombs. Same thing if it goes in the
opposite
direction. If C has 12 lines, one, two,
three,
four, five, six, seven, eight, nine, ten,
eleven,
twelve. If C has 12 lines, then what will
its
charge be? Well, 12 lines is double that
of
over here in A, so we know that our charge
for
C would be equal to double that of the
charge
of A, 20 Coulombs.
Now, this can be used for anything, even
if
it's the opposite charge as well.
For example, let's say charge D this time
is
negatively charged, but it has three
arrows
going towards it. Based off of A, if A has
six
arrows and its magnitude is 10, then the
magnitude
of this would be five. Even though the
sign
is different because it's negative, the
magnitude
would be five. So we base off the density
of
the electric field lines and the number of
electric
field lines we have to quantify our data.
Let's have another example.
Let's say we have a charge over here
of positive five Coulombs, and
we have another charge over here of
negative
15 Coulombs. So
how will we draw the electric field
diagrams
towards this? Well, we know that the
electric
field lines are going to be going towards
the
negative lines, but we don't know how
many.
And to do that, we could literally use
what
we've just learned, the density. So the
negative
one should have three times the amount of
lines
as this one. So let's just pretend that
this
one has four lines.
I'm probably going to draw one of these
lines
to go away like that, and then another one
like
that. One, two, three, four, four.
And now, since this has four lines, we'll
need
three times four is 12 lines for this one.
We already have one here, so we need 11
more.
So we could do one, two, one, two,
three, four, five, six, seven,
eight, nine, ten, eleven.
And this would be a rough estimate of what
this
diagram would look like. So this has four
lines,
and this has four times three, or 15 over
12,
negative 15 over five, sorry, equals 12
lines.
So the number of lines really depends on
just
the ratio of the magnitude of the charges.
And that's basically electric field lines
and
how you calculate them. Thank you for
listening,
and we'll see you in the next one. Bye!